Finding Aid for Everett L. Kelly Papers 1926-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Everett L. Kelly Papers 1926-1986
Kelly, Everett Lowell, 1905-
3 linear feet
Professor of psychology at the University of Michigan. Papers include an unpublished autobiography; files relating to his work with the Civil Aeronautics Administration during World War II in developing a pilot aptitude test and a flight training manual; and correspondence and subject files relating to his professional activities and research on such subjects as color-hearing, extrasensory perception, a marriage longitudinal study, and predictors for student success; also papers detailing his work on the Thalia Massie rape case; and photographs.
88402 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Kelly's daughter, Patricia Kelly Klinger (donor no. 7544 ). The collection was received in various accessions in 1988.
The collection is open for research.
Everett Lowell Kelly, born November 15, 1905, came to the University of Michigan as a professor of psychology in 1946, already a distinguished member of his profession. He was an outstanding student at Purdue (B.A., 1926), Colorado State College of Education (M.A., 1928), and Stanford University (PhD, 1930). His first academic position was at the University of Hawaii, where he encountered Thalia Massie and later became involved in her well-publicized rape trial. During World War II Kelly was active in the Civil Aeronautics Administration, developing a pilot aptitude test and a flight training manual which standardized vocabularies for naval flight instructors. In 1945 he spent a year in Washington, D.C. working closely with scientists and senators involved in creating a National Science Foundation.
At the University of Michigan, Kelly and department chairman Donald Marquis worked hard to build up the then weak psychology department by hiring reputable faculty and developing the curriculum. When Marquis left in 1957, Kelly was named chairman of the department. He retired from formal teaching in 1974.
Kelly's professional interests were many and varied; over the years he explored such subjects as "color hearing," extrasensory perception, personality and compatibility in marriage (later published as the well known Kelly Longitudinal Study), training programs, predictors for student success, and methods of testing. He was active in a variety of organizations and agencies including the American Psychological Association (member of board of directors and president, 1954-1955), Veterans Administration, Office of Naval Research, Peace Corps, National Institute of Mental Health, and the Psychological Corporation.
Kelly maintained a lifelong interest in amateur radio, through which he met and courted his second wife, Lillian. Kelly died on January 16, 1986.
The Everett Kelly collection is arranged into four series. The bulk of the collection relates to his professional interests outside of the University of Michigan.
Subjects:
Color-hearing.; Extrasensory perception.; Kelly, E. Lowell (Everett Lowell), 1905-1986; Longitudinal method.; Massie, Thalia Fortescue, 1910 or 11-1963.; Psychology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Kelly, E. Lowell (Everett Lowell), 1905-1986; Kelly family.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical
  The first Biographical series includes Kelly's autobiography, vitas, military information, and materials on personal interests such as amateur radio, inventions, and his wife Lillian.
  - Autobiography-Early (Box 1)
  - Autobiography (Box 1)
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - Kelly, Lillian (wife) (Box 1)
  - Radio Amateurs (Box 1)
  - Patents (Box 1)
- Military and War Materials 1939-1945
  The series Military and War Material, 1939-1945, is largely related to his work on developing flight training manuals for the Civil Aeronautics Administration, and also contains correspondence from World War II years.
  - Civil Aeronautics Administration
    - Correspondence, John G. Jenkins 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, A-Z. 1939-1942, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Form Letters, Lists (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - "A Preliminary Study of Certain Predictors of Success in Civilian Pilot Training" (Box 1)
    - Reports (Box 1)
    - Training Manual 1943 (Box 1)
  - Institute of the Aeronautical Services 1941 (Box 1)
  - Navy Commission 1942 (Box 1)
  - World War II 1943-1945, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - World War II, Vouchers 1944 (Box 1)
- Professional 1926-1985
  The series Professional, 1926-1985, is divided into two subseries, Correspondence, 1932-1985 and Subject Files, 1926-1985. Both these subseries document Kelly's professional interests including schooling, studies, controversies such as the Thalia Massie case, his Longitudinal Study, school curriculum, his work on color hearing (chromaesthia) and extrasensory perception, the "nature vs. nurture" controversy, and copies of his many publications.
  - Correspondence 1932-1985
    - Personal 1932-1933 (Box 1)
    - Louis Terman 1934-1937 (Box 1)
    - A-H 1939-1942 (Box 1)
    - I-Z 1939-1942 (Box 1)
    - Elliot, E.C. 1939-1942 (Box 1)
    - Knight, Dr. F.S. 1940-1942 (Box 1)
    - Personal 1938-1985, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Subject Files 1926-1985
    - American Association for Applied Psychology 1942 (Box 2)
    - Adult Behavior Disturbances (Box 2)
    - Annual Report 1941, 1942 (Box 2)
    - American Psychological Association, President (Box 2)
    - Art Aptitude Test 1929 (Box 2)
    - Chromaesthesia/Mescal Experiment 1930 (Box 2)
    - Chromaesthesia Data 1930 (Box 2)
    - Chromaesthesia Thesis 1930 (Box 2)
    - Computer Program 1955 (Box 2)
    - Copyright (Box 2)
    - Extrasensory Perception 1938 (Box 2)
    - Foundation Fund 1953-1954 (Box 2)
    - Future Research (Box 2)
    - Graphology 1938-1940 (Box 2)
    - Homosexuality (Box 2)
    - Huron Valley Child Guidance Center 1982-1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Hutt, Max 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Kelly Longitudinal Study 1979-1981, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Medical School Student Evaluation (Box 2)
    - Nature vs. Nurture Controversy 1974 (Box 2)
    - Notebooks-Universität Berlin 1932 (Box 2)
    - Notes for talks (Box 2)
    - Notes-Terman (Box 2)
    - National Research (Box 2)
    - Council 1939-1942 (Box 2)
    - Peace Corps (Box 2)
    - Personality Forms (Box 2)
    - Personality over the Air 1938-1940 (Box 2)
    - Purdue Marriage Course (Box 2)
    - Radcliffe College-Henry A. Murray Research Center (Box 2)
    - Massie Case
      - General 1967 (Box 2)
      - Blood and Orchids (Box 3)
        (novel)
      - Rape in Paradise (Box 3)
    - Reports/Publications, A-Z (Box 3)
    - School Psychological Counselors 1950 (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1961-1964, unbound (Box 3)
    - Sensory deprivation 1962 (Box 3)
    - Social Science Research Committee on Appraisal of Methods of Prediction 1940-1941 (Box 3)
    - Student Attitudes Study 1935 (Box 3)
    - Stanford University-Class Notes (Box 3)
    - Terman Commemorative Volume 1940 (Box 3)
    - Thesis-Purdue 1926 (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan Psychology Department (Box 3)
    - Vacuum Tube Voltmeter 1935 (Box 3)
    - Vassar Study 1934-1937 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes portraits, and photos of Kelly with colleagues and family.
  - Armed Services (Box 3)
  - Family (Box 3)
  - Professional (Box 3)